Welcome to JW Broadcasting!
JW Broadcastingにようこそ!
In this month’s program,
we’ll meet a brother who preaches
今月のプログラムでは インド手話の区域で
宣べ伝えている一人の兄弟にお会いします
in the Indian Sign Language field.
その難しい割り当てに対する
兄弟の見方から何を学べるでしょうか?
What can we learn from his view
of the challenges he faces
in his assignment?
羊はエホバに属しています
Jehovah’s sheep
belong to him.
This dramatization
shows a special way
このドラマは ご自分の羊の
群れを世話するために—
that Jehovah uses shepherds
in the congregation
エホバが会衆の牧者を特別な仕方で
用いることを示しています
to care for his flock.
また あなたは初めて
神の名前を知った人が—
And have you witnessed
the life-changing moment
when someone
生き方を変化させた瞬間を
目撃したことがありますか？
first learns God’s name?
We’ll see the results of this sister’s
lifelong search to know the true God.
真の神を長年探し求めていたこの姉妹が
どうなったかを見てみましょう
This and much more is ahead
2016年6月の
JW Broadcastingから—
on the June 2016 edition
さらに多くのことを
ご覧いただけるでしょう！
of JW Broadcasting!
エホバの民は
神の言葉を学ぶことが—
Jehovah’s people have always considered
the studying of his Word
常に生活の重要な部分を
占めるべきであると考えています
to be an essential part of life.
God’s Law to Israel commanded
that the king “must read from [the Law]
イスラエルに対する神の律法は その王が
“命の日の限り [律法]を読まなければならない—”
all the days of his life, so that he
may learn to fear Jehovah his God.”
“それは 自分の神エホバを恐れることを
学ぶためである”と命じていました
In the Mayan territories
of Yucatán, Mexico,
メキシコのユカタン州の
マヤ語の区域では—
our brothers are helping people
learn to read God’s Word for themselves.
自分で神の言葉を読むよう
兄弟たちが地元の人々を援助しています
People’s lives change when they
can finally read the Bible on their own
聖書を読めるようになると
生活は変化し—
and more readily ‘learn
to fear Jehovah their God.’
より早く“自分の神エホバを恐れることを
学ぶ”ようになります
地球上の6人に1人は
読み方を知りません
One out of every six people on earth
doesn’t know how to read.
世界中のエホバの証人は—
Jehovah’s Witnesses
around the world
こうした人々を助けるために
識字クラスを組織しました
have organized literacy classes
to help such ones.
読むのは苦手です
I don’t like to read.
集会中は寝ていました
I used to sleep at the meetings.
わたしたちの区域では たいていの人は
マヤ語を話しますが—
In our territory,
most people speak the Mayan language,
but very few can read it.
読める人はほとんどいません
わたしが講演をして
聖句を引用するときには—
On occasion I would give a talk,
and when I would
cite a scripture,
most of the audience would look it up.
聴衆はその聖句を見ますが—
But then I would see
a blank stare on their faces
読めないので—
ぽかんとした顔をしているのです
because they
couldn’t read the text.
エホバとその言葉を学びたかったので—
I was moved
to learn how to read
読み方を学ぶようになりました
because I wanted to learn about Jehovah
and study his Word, the Bible.
一人の姉妹が家に来て
教えてくれました
So a sister came
to my house to teach me.
Literacy classes are often conducted
on an individual level.
識字クラスは個人のレベルに
応じて開かれます
聖書研究の後 少しの時間を使って
読み方を練習します
After a person has had their Bible study,
they can spend some time
to practice reading skills.
この訓練から益を受けることのできる人が
大勢いることが長老たちに認められると—
But when
the local elders notice
that there are many
that can benefit from this training,
王国会館でのもっと大きな
クラスが計画されます
they can schedule
a larger class
at the Kingdom Hall.
この目的のために使用されるテキストは—
The study material used
for this purpose is the brochure
「読み書きに励む」というブロシュアーです
Apply Yourself to Reading and Writing.
It’s available in 30 languages
in the Central America branch territory.
それは中央アメリカ支部の管轄区域の
30の言語で入手できます
クラスに入っている生徒の
助けになるのであれば—
Other study materials can be used
as well, as long as they help
ほかの資料も使用することができます
the development of the students
enrolled in the class.
And we use a board
on which we write,
発音の難しい言葉を黒板に書きます
for instance, words
that are difficult to pronounce.
これは複雑な言葉を読む助けとなります
This helps in the reading
of complicated words.
There are some who are,
well, very quick learners.
とても早く学ぶことの
できる人も幾人かいます
一方で 一語一語学ぶ人もいます
On the other hand,
others go word by word.
でも 練習するにつれて
正しく読むことを学び始めます
But as they practice,
they start getting the hang of it.
I’m good at masonry work,
わたしは石工の仕事は上手ですが
読むのは苦手です
but learning to read
is not easy.
この年齢で読むには努力がいります
Reading at his age
is a big challenge.
生徒の学び方が異なっている
ことを理解すべきです
You need to understand
that each student learns differently.
人によっては とても辛抱強く
なければなりません
With some,
you need to be very patient.
書き方を学んだ最初の
言葉は エホバでした
The first word
I learned to write was Jehovah.
“こう書くんです”というと—
“It’s like this,” I tell him.
“辛抱強く教えてくれない
からだよ”と言われました
He says, “It’s ‘cause
you’re not being patient with me!”
Having a sense of humor
is a big help in the learning process,
ユーモアのセンスは 間違いや失敗に
注意を向けないための大きな助けです
so as not to focus
on errors and mistakes.
1946年にメキシコで
記録を取り始めて以来—
Since 1946, when records
began being taken in Mexico,
15万2千人以上が
読み書きを学びました
more than 152,000 people
have learned to read and write,
払われた努力に感謝しています
thanks to these training efforts.
メキシコ州の教育長官は—
The Secretary of Public Education
この識字クラスが地元市民に対して行なった
仕事や大きな援助に感謝しています
in the State of Mexico
has recognized the work and the great help
these literacy classes
have been to the local citizens.
学んだスキルは日々の生活で
助けとなっているだけでなく—
The skills they learn
help in their day-to-day life,
エホバについてさらに学び—
but also it helps them
to learn more about Jehovah
他の人を教えることができるように
なるための助けとなっています
and to be able to teach others.
以前は話すことを
全部覚えましたが—
I used to have to memorize
everything I was going to say,
今では聖書から直接
短い聖句を読むことができます
but now I can read
short scriptures to people
directly from the Bible.
進歩するにつれて 生徒たちは—
As the students progress
in the class, they demonstrate
テモテ第一 4:15の “あなたの進歩が
すべての人に明らかになるようにしなさい”
the words found
at 1 Timothy 4:15,
which says in part
という聖句を実証する
ことになります
“so that your advancement
may be plainly seen by all people.”
クラスの益は生徒たちの中に
明らかに見られます
And these benefits
are plainly seen in the students.
夫はアルコール中毒で たばこを吸い
汚ない言葉を話していました
My husband was an alcoholic,
he smoked,
and he used bad language.
But he made big changes
in his life,
でも 大きな変化を遂げました
and we see that this training
has been a big help.
この訓練が大きな助けとなりました
We really see
these great blessings.
すばらしい祝福です
バプテスマを受けました
Reading helped me
to get baptized.
Helping other people
to improve their reading skills
朗読の技術を改善するよう
助けることができてとても幸福です
makes me feel very happy.
情報を読んで理解することから来る
喜びの表情を見ることができるのは最高です
I feel great because I see
on their face the joy they get
from reading and understanding
the information.
大きな益を受けました
Well, I’ve benefited so much.
今では家族で一緒に聖書を読めます
For instance,
now we read the Bible
together as a family.
とても幸せです
It makes me very happy.
家族が以前よりも一致しました
We’re more united as a family.
Our children
respect my husband more,
子どもたちは父親を敬っています
like the father he is.
今 奉仕の僕です
Now I’m a ministerial servant.
When I go preaching
door to door,
家から家の伝道に行くと
“読めない”という人がいます
some people say,
“I don’t know how to read.”
でも こう言います
But then I tell them,
わたしも読めませんでしたが
エホバについて学びました
“I didn’t know either,
but I learned about Jehovah.
あなたもできます
And you can too!”
わたしができたのですから
だれでもできます
If I learned to read,
anybody can.
Our theme for this month
今月のテーマは “ますます互いのことを
考え 鼓舞し 励まし合う” です
is “Consider, Incite, and Encourage
One Another All the More So.”
JW Broadcasting
皆さんがJW Broadcastingを
とても楽しんでおられるのはなぜですか？
—why do we enjoy it so much?
Many of you have expressed
how the monthly broadcast draws you closer
多くの皆さんは
おかげで兄弟姉妹や—
エホバの組織を身近に感じる
ようになれたと述べています
to our brothers and sisters
and to Jehovah’s organization.
家から出られず孤立しているなら
特にこのプログラムは楽しみでしょう
If you’re homebound or isolated,
you especially treasure these programs.
And yet, while we appreciate
the advances in technology
でも こういう技術の進歩には
感謝しつつも—
皆さんは会衆の集会に出席して
兄弟姉妹と一緒になりたい—
that have made all of this possible,
we know that your sincere desire
という誠実な願いを抱いて
おられることでしょう
is to be present
with your brothers and sisters in person
at our congregation meetings.
世界中のエホバの証人は
同じように感じています
Jehovah’s Witnesses
around the world share this feeling.
フィンランド北部の冬は
とりわけ寒くなります
In northern Finland, for example,
winters are especially cold,
even by Finnish standards.
時にはー50℃まで下がります
At times, temperatures plummet
to minus 50 degrees Celsius,
or minus 58 degrees Fahrenheit!
この状況では 運転をしたり—
Under those conditions,
it’s very difficult to drive,
ましてや長い距離を歩いたり
することはとても困難です
much less walk long distances.
でも兄弟たちは集まることを
楽しみにしています
Still, the brothers love
to gather together.
どうするのでしょうか？
How do they manage it?
ある小さな村の一人の兄弟は
王国会館の近くに住んでいて—
In one small village, there is a brother
who lives near the Kingdom Hall
暖房の効くガレージを持っています
and has a warm garage.
On meeting nights, he uses his car
集会の晩に 兄弟は車で会衆の
それぞれの家族を会館まで運びます
to bring each family
in the congregation to the hall.
Then he parks in his garage and runs
the short distance back to the Kingdom Hall.
その後 車をガレージに止めて
王国会館まで走って戻るのです
When the meeting is over, he returns
all the friends safely to their homes.
集会後 皆を家まで
安全に送り届けます
In the Bible,
gatherings for pure worship
聖書では 清い崇拝のために集まることは
仲間との個人的な交わりの機会でした
were occasions for personal association
with fellow believers.
そのためには指定された場所に
出かけなければならず—
Such association required travel
to a designated place.
労力 犠牲 危険が伴いました
This involved work,
sacrifice, even risk.
出エジプト記 34:24が述べていること
を考えてみてください
Consider what is stated
at Exodus 34:24.
この節は すべての
イスラエルの男子が年3回—
This verse has to do with the command
that every Israelite male
エルサレムでの祭りのために集まるように
との命令に関連しています
should gather three times a year
for the festivals in Jerusalem.
これは何を意味したでしょうか？
What would that mean
in practical terms?
土地を守る男子が
一人もいなくなるなら—
Wouldn’t the nation
be left vulnerable to attack
if no men were left
to guard the land?
民は敵の攻撃にさらされるが
ままになるのでしょうか？
And if word spread
among the surrounding nations
毎年 定期的に年3回—
that practically everyone
congregated in Jerusalem
すべての者がエルサレムに集まる
といううわさが近隣諸国に広まるなら—
three times a year,
like clockwork, year after year,
敵がやって来て イスラエルの村や都市を
侵略するのではないでしょうか？
wouldn’t it be just a matter of time
before some invading army
would come
and pillage an Israelite city?
出エジプト記 34:24には
エホバの驚くべき答えがあります
At Exodus 34:24,
we find
Jehovah’s remarkable answer:
“For I will drive the nations
away from before you,
and I will enlarge your territory,
and nobody will desire,”
yes, even desire, “your land
“while you are going up to see
the face of Jehovah your God
そうです 欲することさえないのです
three times a year.”
Jehovah kept that promise.
エホバはその約束を守られました
It’s a historical fact
that from 1513 B.C.E.
西暦前1513年から西暦66年にいたる
までの期間 この年3回の祭りの期間は—
all the way down to 66 C.E.
no foreign nation ever came
どの諸国もイスラエルの領地を
侵略しなかったことは歴史の事実です
to invade Israelite territory
during those three annual festivals.
エホバはご自分の民が ずっと
共に集まることを重視しておられました
Jehovah placed high value
on having his people
gather together
in the same space.
クリスチャンの時代において
使徒パウロはコリント第一 14:23で—
In the Christian era,
the apostle Paul wrote
at 1 Corinthians 14:23
about ‘the whole congregation
“会衆全体が一つの場所に集まる”
ことについて書きました
coming together to one place.’
Now, although modern broadcasting
technology didn’t exist in those days,
当時は 現代のブロードキャスティングの
技術はありませんでしたが—
手紙などの有効な手段がありました
there were other viable methods
of communicating, such as writing letters,
実際に同じ場所にいなくても
コミュニケーションをとることは可能でした
that didn’t require people to be physically
present in the same location.
Still, the apostle John,
though a capable writer,
使徒ヨハネは有能な筆者でしたが
ヨハネ第二 12にあるように—
preferred face-to-face interchange
with fellow Christians
仲間のクリスチャンと向かい合って
交友を持つことのほうを好みました
as he expressed
at 2 John 12.
Or consider what is stated
また ヨブ 1:6について
考えてみてください
at Job 1:6:
“Now the day came
when the sons of the true God
entered to take their station
before Jehovah.”
Job 2:1 speaks
of another such day.
ヨブ 2:1は 同様の別の日に
ついて述べています
Just imagine!
考えてみてください
Here Jehovah himself,
あらゆるコミュニケーション手段を
自由に活用できるにもかかわらず—
though having all conceivable methods
of communication at his disposal,
エホバは天の霊の被造物のために
特別な日を定め—
set specific days
for his spirit creatures in heaven
彼らがご自分の前に
集まるようにされました
to assemble
in his immediate presence.
明らかに聖書は—
Clearly, the Scriptures encourage
regular personal association
神の仲間の僕たちとの定期的で個人的な
交わりを持つことを励ましています
with fellow servants of God.
現代の通信技術を利用して集まりに
仮想参加できるのはうれしいことですが—
Virtual attendance through modern
communication technology has value,
and we’re happy to use it,
but it’s no substitute for being together.
それは兄弟たちと共にいることに
取って代わるものではありません
And why not?
なぜでしょうか？
それは会衆と交わることが
成し遂げる事柄のためです
Because of what association
with the congregation achieves.
It’s not just that we receive nutritious
and varied spiritual food.
それは 栄養価の高い価値ある
霊的食物を得るだけのことではありません
Meetings inform us,
but so does JW Broadcasting.
集会は知識を与えます
JW Broadcastingも同じです
Meetings encourage us,
but so does JW Broadcasting.
集会は励みを与えます
JW Broadcastingもそうです
Fellow Christians who offer comments
and sing from the heart build us up,
仲間のクリスチャンの注解や
心からの歌は築き上げます
and yet we can hear that also
on JW Broadcasting.
JW Broadcastingでも
同様のことを聞くことができます
It’s when we’re together
—all together in one place—
でも 一緒になり 一か所に集まるときに
ほかの人はこちらの声を聞き—
that others can hear us
and draw encouragement
わたしたちの心からの確信 笑顔
握手によって励みを受けます
from our heartfelt convictions,
our smile, our handshake.
集会は 兄弟姉妹のことを時間や
注意や関心を払うに値する人々だと—
Meetings give us opportunities
to show our brothers and sisters
that we esteem them
as worthy of our time,
わたしたちが評価していることを
示す機会を与えてくれます
attention, and concern.
だからこそ わたしたちは
家から出られず—
That is why we go and visit our brothers
who are homebound or isolated
孤独を感じている兄弟たちを訪問し
彼らを愛していることを示すのです
because we want to show them
that we love them.
Moreover, in a special way,
さらに 集会は特別な仕方で
聖霊の影響の下にわたしたちを導きます
our meetings bring us
under the influence of holy spirit.
At Revelation 2:7,
啓示 2:7で 栄光を受けた
イエスは言いました
the glorified Jesus said:
“Let the one
who has an ear hear
what the spirit says
to the congregations.”
We need that spirit
to help us resist temptation,
わたしたちは 誘惑に抵抗し
勇気を保ち 宣教に備え—
to embolden and equip us
for the ministry,
健全な決定を下すことができるように
なる点で聖霊の助けが必要です
and to enable us
to make sound decisions.
Still, there’s a reason
to attend meetings
集会は 楽しい交わり
平和的な雰囲気 真のさわやかさ—
that’s even more important
than the pleasant company,
連帯感 与える機会を提供しますし
エホバの聖霊を受けるための手段ですが—
the peaceful atmosphere,
the genuine refreshment,
the sense of belonging,
the opportunities to give,
それに加えてもうひとつ 集会に出席する
さらに一層重要な理由があります
or even the fact that meetings
are a means by which
we receive
Jehovah’s holy spirit.
The key reason
why we gather together
共に集まり合うための一番重要な理由は
詩編 26:12に述べられています
is stated at Psalm 26:12:
“My foot is standing
on level ground;
in the great congregation,
I will praise Jehovah.”
Yes, the principal reason
why we gather together in person
そうです 個人として
共に集まり合う主要な理由は—
エホバが受けるにふさわしい
ものを差し出すためです
is to give Jehovah what he deserves
—praise, glory, yes, worship.
それは 賛美と栄光と崇拝です
集会に出席するなら—
Our meeting attendance
shows Jehovah
エホバとみ子に近づきたいと
願っていることを示すことになります
that we want to draw close
to him and his Son.
あふれるほどの愛のうちに
エホバはさらに多くの人が—
In his abundant love, Jehovah invites
many more to serve him and keep living.
ご自分に仕え 生き続ける
ように招いておられます
Because he lives eternally,
Jehovah can nurture
those relationships forever.
エホバは永久に生きられるので
エホバとの関係も永続します
The Adversary can offer
no such hope of endless life,
敵対者は終わりのない希望を
差し伸べることができないので—
so he promotes selfishness,
pride, and other negative traits
利己心や誇り その他の消極的な傾向を
あおり 同じ部屋にいたり—
that isolate people from one another,
even when they are in the same room,
同じ活動をしたりしていても
人々を互いに孤立させています
engaged in the same activities.
In contrast, our great God
is drawing his people
対照的に わたしたちの偉大な神は—
closer to himself,
to his Son,
人々をご自分とみ子に
また互いに引き寄せてくださり—
and to one another
so that we “may all be one,”
イエスがヨハネ 17:21で
祈ったように—
as Jesus prayed
as recorded at John 17:21.
わたしたちが“みな一つになる”
ようにしてくださいます
And it’s not just the act
of converging
それは わたしたちが
互いに一致するために—
on the same location
that unites us either.
単に同じ場所に集まる
という行為ではありません
Lots of people coexist in the same space
when they go to a market,
多くの人は スーパーに行ったり
スポーツイベントに出かけたり—
attend a sporting event,
or use public transportation.
公共の乗り物に乗ったりして
同じ空間を共有します
Crowding of itself
does not equate with unity.
集まることそれ自体が一致している
ということではありません
What makes the true
Christian congregation different?
真のクリスチャン会衆の違いは何ですか？
Notice how Hebrews chapter 10,
ヘブライ 10:24, 25がその質問に
どう答えているか注目してください
verses 24 and 25
answers this question.
Now here we find
the divinely inspired standard
そこには 神の霊感によって定められた
すべての集まりのための基準が見出せます
for all our gatherings:
“And let us
consider one another so as to incite
“to love and fine works,
not forsaking our meeting together,
“as some have the custom,
but encouraging one another,
“and all the more so as you see
the day drawing near.”
Now, what does it mean
to “consider one another”?
“互いのことをよく考える”とは—
また “愛とりっぱな業とを鼓舞し合う”
とはどういう意味でしょうか？
What does it mean
“to incite to love and fine works”?
And in what way might we
‘encourage one another’?
そして どのように
“互いに励まし合う”のでしょうか？
“考える”とは
“関心を払う 注意を払う”という意味です
The verb “consider”
could also be rendered
“be concerned about;
pay attention to.”
ですから “互いのことを
よく考える”には—
So when
we “consider one another,”
we show interest
that goes far beyond a brief greeting.
単に挨拶をする以上の関心を
示さなければなりません
And when we pay careful attention
to one another, we’re better prepared
また お互いがよく注意を払うなら
鼓舞し合う備えができ—
to incite, that is, to motivate one another,
to stir one another to action.
お互いのために行動するよう促されます
And how might we do this?
これをどのように行なえますか？
Not by making comparisons
or shaming our brothers,
比較したり 兄弟たちに恥ずかしい
思いをさせたりするのではなく—
for that would hardly be
“encouraging one another,”
仲間の心を元気付けることによって
“互いに励まし合う”ことができます
we endeavor to lift one another’s hearts
when we’re together.
And when we do this
to the best of our ability,
できる限りそうするなら
後はエホバの霊が働き—
then we can be confident
that Jehovah’s spirit will do the rest,
兄弟たちは励まされたと
感じることでしょう
and that our brothers
will feel strengthened.
It’s evident, then,
that true worship
真の崇拝とは参加することであり
行動が求められます
means participation;
it requires a response.
その良い例は 兄弟姉妹が一緒に
歌うときに与えたり得たりする励ましです
Another noteworthy example of this
is the encouragement we both give
and receive when we sing together
with our brothers and sisters.
2月の週日の集会で
取り上げられましたが—
In ancient Israel,
at times they had a chorus,
ネヘミヤ 12章にあるように—
such as the one described
in Nehemiah chapter 12
古代イスラエルでは
時々コーラスが歌われました
that we talked about
in our midweek meeting back in February.
イスラエルの歌の多くは
交唱形式 つまり—
Much of Israel’s group singing
was antiphonal,
ある歌い手たちにほかの歌い手たちが
答え応じて歌う形式でした
that is, some of the singers
prompted others to respond.
たとえば 詩編 106編は—
For instance, Psalm 106
which begins and ends with the words
“ヤハを賛美せよ”または“ハレルヤ”
という言葉で始まり 終わっていますが—
“Praise Jah!” or “Hallelujah!”
encouraged the people
to say in response: “Amen!”
それに対して人々は
“アーメン！”と答え応じます
Psalm 136 was written
詩編 136編はコーラス同士が
互いに呼応しあう形式になっています
to allow for different choruses
to answer one another.
コーラス同士が交互にこのような歌詞を
歌い合うのを想像してみてください
Now just imagine
responding choruses
singing these alternating lines:
“Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good;
“his loyal love endures forever.
“Give thanks to the God of gods,
“for his loyal love endures forever.
“Give thanks to the Lord of lords,
for his loyal love endures forever.”
And on it went for 26 verses!
これが26節まで続くのです
今日まで 歌は
エホバの善良さに対する—
To this day,
singing demonstrates
our heartfelt response
to the goodness of Jehovah.
わたしたちの気持ちを
表わす手段となっています
エホバへの深い気持ちを表現する仲間と
一緒に歌えるのはうれしいことです
What a joy it is to sing
in company with others who are moved
to pour out the depths
of their feelings to Jehovah!
And now at our Kingdom Halls,
we’re accompanied by orchestral renderings
今では歌の多くが
オーケストラの伴奏になっているので—
王国会館での週日や週末の集会で
一緒に歌えるのはうれしいことです
of many of our songs
—another reason to sing out
at our midweek
and weekend meetings.
新しい形式の週日の集会を
どのように楽しんでおられますか？
And speaking of the midweek meeting,
how are you enjoying the new format?
More of the program is devoted
to delving into the Bible itself.
プログラムの多くは聖書そのものを
掘り下げるようになっています
Time spent on preparing us
for our public ministry
これまで公の宣教の準備の
ために用いてきた時間を—
focuses more than ever
on situations we face in field service.
一層野外奉仕で直面する状況に
備えるために用いています
And the meetings move along
at a satisfying pace.
集会は満足のいくペースで進みます
Yes, JW Broadcasting
is a wonderful blessing,
そうです JW Broadcastingは
すばらしい祝福です
a powerful means to talk to
and fortify our brothers
世界中の兄弟たちに同時に話をして
強めるための強力な道具です
around the world
—simultaneously.
でも 仲間の神の僕と共に
会衆の集会において—
Still, nothing can replace
the experience
of worshipping Jehovah
in concert
エホバを崇拝するという経験に
取って替わるものは何もありません
with our fellow servants of God
at congregation meetings.
When a meeting concludes
and we lift our heads
集会が終わって—
閉会の祈りのあと
頭を上げるとき—
after the final prayer,
we find ourselves surrounded
エホバを愛し その主権を擁護している
人々に囲まれているのを感じます
by others who love Jehovah
and support his sovereignty.
こうした大切な益については
2016年4月号の研究記事—
These important benefits
are detailed
in the April 2016
study article
「崇拝のために集まり合うべきなのは
なぜですか」で詳しく扱われています
“Why Should We Meet
Together for Worship?”
This month, we’re studying
that article worldwide.
今月その記事を世界中で学びます
Later, in October,
we begin a special campaign
その後10月には 人々を集会に招待する
ための特別なキャンペーンが行なわれます
to invite the public
to our meetings.
If you do not yet regularly associate
with Jehovah’s Witnesses
まだエホバの証人と定期的に
交わっておられないなら—
あるいは自分の会衆から
離れて旅行しているなら—
or if you travel away
from your congregation, use jw.org
jw.org を使って近くの
集会場所を探してください
to find a meeting you can attend.
Click: “About Us,” “Meetings,”
「エホバの証人について」「集会」そして
「最寄りの会場を探す」をクリックするか—
and “Find a Location Near You”
or simply scroll to the bottom
あるいはjw.orgのどのページでも
一番下までスクロールして—
of any jw.org page
and click “Attend Our Meetings.”
「集会に出席する」をクリックします
At our meetings,
you’ll experience what it means
集会に出席するなら
あなたは 考えたり鼓舞したり—
to consider, incite, and ‘encourage
one another all the more so
“その日が近づくのを見てますます
互いに励まし合ったりする”とは—
どういうことかを経験なさるでしょう
as we see
the day drawing near.’
We’ve discussed
vital ways we benefit
崇拝のためにクリスチャンの集会に集まって
益を得るための重要な方法について考えました
when we come together
for worship at Christian meetings.
What many notice
エホバの証人の集会に
初めて出席した多くの人は—
when they first attend meetings
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
神のお名前エホバがよく用いられて
いることに気づきます
is that they hear
God’s name, Jehovah.
このライフ・ストーリーでは—
In this life story,
Soten Yoeun relates the impact
ソテン・ユーエンがカンボジアの
虐殺現場を生き残った後—
that learning God’s name
had on her
神のお名前について知ったときの
感動について語ります
after surviving
the killing fields of Cambodia.
On the killing fields
in Cambodia,
大量殺りくが行なわれた
カンボジアのキリングフィールドで—
わたしは神に祈りました
I prayed to God,
でもその名前を知りませんでした
but I didn’t know his name.
When I was a very young girl,
まだ幼かった頃 家族は引き離され—
they separated our family
and they put me
to work in the rice field
わたしは朝の5時から夜の9時まで
水田で働かされました
from five in the morning
till nine in the evening.
他の子どもたちが死んでいくのを見ると—
When you see
some other children that get killed,
絶望的になって助けを
叫び求めたくなるものです
you really desperately cry
for help inside.
次は自分だと思うからです
You always think
that you are next.
でもわたしは
真の神がどこかにいて—
But in my heart I always believed
that there had to be a true God
切り抜けられるよう助けて
下さると信じていました
somewhere, somehow
that can help me get through this.
1年後 わたしの家族は
カンボジアから逃れることにしました
One year later,
my family decided to escape Cambodia.
6-7か月程かけて
タイまで歩いて行きました
We walk close to six
or seven months to Thailand.
わたしは20人きょうだいでしたが—
And I have 20 brothers and sisters
生き残ったのは 4人だけでした
—only 4 of us survived.
わたしには目の不自由な伯母がいて—
I have a blind aunt that holds
on my shoulder all the time.
いつもわたしの肩につかまっていました
But one day, we got caught.
ある日 わたしたちは
捕らえられてしまいました
As they start shooting,
I push my aunt down to the ground
彼らが射撃を始めると—
わたしは伯母と共に地面に倒れこみ
死んだふりをしました
and try to pretend
that we are dead.
And when I get up,
起き上がったときには
両親の姿はありませんでした
I had no idea
where my parent was.
何か月もジャングルで過ごしました
We spent
many months in the jungle.
As I try to survive,
生き残るため 何でも食べました
I eat whatever I can find,
and I also help my auntie to survive.
伯母のことも助けなければなりませんでした
One day when I go
out to look for food,
ある日 食べ物を探すために
遠くまで歩いてゆくうちに—
I walked so far away
帰り道がわからなくなってしまいました
I couldn’t find my way back.
大きな木の下で泣きはじめ—
I start crying really hard
underneath a tree
空を仰いで—
and look up to the sky
真の神に祈りました
and pray to the true God.
I was raised as a child
to pray to Buddhas.
ブッダに祈るよう
教えられて育ちましたが—
But on this night
その晩は ブッダではなく—
when I start praying,
I specifically said
that I’m not praying
to Buddha
真の神に祈りました
—I’m praying
to the true God.
そして “真の神よ
もしおられるのでしたらー”
And I say,
“True God,
if you are really here,
“please help me
“どうか助けてください
とっても怖いです”
“because I am really scared
“お腹も空いて 寒いんです”
と祈りました
and I’m hungry
and I’m cold.”
祈り終わると 木の下で
眠り込んでしまいました
After I pray, I just fall to sleep
under the big tree.
Eventually, I make it
into the refugee camp in Thailand,
ついにわたしは
タイの難民キャンプに収容され—
家族とも再会できました
and I was reunited
with my family.
We lived in the refugee camp
in Thailand
10年ほど難民キャンプで過ごした後—
for about ten years
before we come to United States.
アメリカに渡りました
そして引き続き真の神を探し—
My searching for the true God,
it didn’t stop there.
We tried to go
to different churches,
幾つかの教会に通いましたが
何も理解できませんでした
but we
didn’t understand anything.
ある日 学校から帰る途中で
ヘロルドという男性に会いました
One day when I come home
from school,
I met this gentlemen
named Herold,
and he asked if he can talk
to me about God.
神について話しても良いかと
尋ねられたので どうぞと言いました
I agree because I saw he have a Bible;
he must be a good man.
彼は聖書を持っていたので
きっと良い人だと思ったからです
When he talked to me,
I tried to pay attention so hard,
彼の話を一生懸命に聴きましたが
よく理解できませんでした
but I still didn’t understand
what he was saying.
それで彼はゆっくり話してくれました
And he went very slow.
“あなたの名前は？”と尋ねられ
“ソテン”と答えると—
And then he said, “Your name?”
I said, “My name Soten.”
And then he said, “Your name, Soten;
my name is Herold.
彼は “あなたはソテン
わたしはヘロルド—”
God’s name, Jehovah.”
“神の名前はエホバ”と言いました
神の名前なんて
考えたこともありませんでした
I never thought
that God had name.
その日以来 エホバのみ名を
決して忘れませんでした
And ever since that day on,
I never forget Jehovah’s name.
心に刻み込まれたからです
It’s superglued in my heart.
He gave me his phone number.
ヘロルドは電話番号を教えてくれ—
He say he gonna ask his wife
to stop by someday,
妻が訪問するようにする
と言ってくれましたが—
but then I move away
from where I lived.
わたしは引っ越してしまいました
Even though I didn’t do
the truth at that time,
まだ真理を学んではいませんでしたが
いつもエホバに祈っていました
I always pray to Jehovah.
神のみ名について知ってから
再び教会に行きましたが—
After I learned God’s name,
I went back to the church.
司祭は“天におられる父よ”
と呼びかけるだけで—
The priest would start out
with “heavenly Father”
but leave out Jehovah’s name.
エホバのお名前をなおざりにしていました
それでわたしは手を挙げました
So I raised my hand.
そして “「天の父よ」と祈るとき—”
I asked him, “Sir,
“when you pray “heavenly Father,”
why don’t you say
“なぜ「天の父 エホバよ」と
呼びかけないのですか？”
“‘heavenly Father, Jehovah’?
Why you not using God’s name?”
“神のお名前を用いない
のですか？”と尋ねました
And then he told me that God
does not force me to be here,
すると司祭は “神は あなたがここに
いるように強要したりはしない”
so I’m welcomed to leave
“出ていったって構わないんだよ”
と言いました
or stay if I want.
彼らがエホバのお名前を
使わないことが分かったので—
So because I realized
that they don’t use
Jehovah’s name,
わたしはそこを去り
二度と戻りませんでした
I left and never returned.
何年も経ってから
ヘロルドに電話をしてみました
And after many years,
I tried to call Herold,
but no one
picked up the phone.
誰も出なかったので
メッセージを残しました
So I leave a message.
わたしのことを覚えていて
くれたらと思いました
I was hoping
that they remembered me.
すると2週間後 ヘロルドが
訪ねてきてくれました
Two weeks later,
Herold comes to my door,
でも その頃は夜に仕事をして
いたため日中は寝ていました
but at the time, I was working at night
and asleep during the day.
それでもヘロルドはあきらめずに
また来てくれました
But Herold never give up;
he come back.
And I keep on praying
to Jehovah,
わたしも 訪ねてきてくれるよう
エホバに祈り続けました
asking for someone
to knock on my door.
And finally, one day
そしてある日 ついに
ヘロルドと会うことができました
I open the door,
and when I saw him,
声もでませんでした
そして涙がこみ上げてきました
I almost couldn’t talk.
I was teared up.
I was so happy to see him
エホバの名前を教えてくれた人と
再会できたのです
because this is the man
who introduced me to Jehovah’s name.
それから一人の姉妹との
聖書研究が始まり—
Eventually, I start
to study with a sister,
霊的に進歩するよう助けられました
and she helped me
grow spiritually.
To know that you have
a heavenly Father
わたしたちのことを顧みてくださる
天の父のことを知るのは—
that cares about you
本当に喜びでした
—that was
the best feeling on earth.
その方についてもっと
知りたいと思うようになり—
It makes me want to know more about him
—want to learn more about him.
“神はこれを好まれますか？
あれはどうですか？”などと—
I would ask questions:
“Did he like this?
Did he like that?”
色々な質問をしました
And then when I go
to the Kingdom Hall,
王国会館に行くとエホバのお名前が
何度も用いられていました
I hear Jehovah’s name
so many times.
ここだ！
I feel, that’s it!
ここがわたしの居場所だと思いました
I found my place.
2013年にバプテスマを受けました
I got baptized in 2013.
My blind aunt that I help her
survive through the jungle,
ジャングルで共に生き残った
伯母は 今でも健在です
she’s still living until today.
そしてエホバについて伯母に
話すことができるのは祝福です
And now that I can get a chance
to talk to her about Jehovah,
that was a blessing.
And I can’t stress enough
真の神がおられること—
how wonderful
それがどなたかということを
知ることができるのは—
and big privilege
that I receive from Jehovah
本当に素晴らしい—
—just to know
who he is and to learn
大きな特権だと感じています
その方にはお名前があります
that there is true God.
その名は—
He have a name,
エホバです
and his name is Jehovah.
姉妹は 冷酷な戦争によって
自分や家族が味わった—
Sister Yoeun
still carries painful memories
from what she and her family suffered
because of man’s ruthless wars.
痛ましい記憶を今も引きずっています
しかし 姉妹には将来の希望と天の父
エホバを知ることからくる慰めとがあり—
But she now has hope
for the future
and the comfort of knowing
her heavenly Father, Jehovah
それはわたしたちも抱いているものです
—something we
all share with her.
姉妹は夫と幼い娘と共に—
Sister Yoeun has the added joy
of worshipping the true God
真の神を崇拝できる増し加えられた
喜びを味わっています
together with her husband
and young daughter.
When we’re at our meetings,
集会において 会衆は
“一人の羊飼い”に従う—
we help the congregation
to stay close together,
“一つの群れ”として一緒に
とどまるように助けられます
part of the “one flock”
that follows the “one shepherd.”
次のドラマでは 一人の若者が
忠実な従属の牧者を通して—
In the following dramatization,
note the way in which one young man
どのようにエホバの愛を示されたかに
注目してみましょう
receives Jehovah’s love
through faithful undershepherds.
ずっと音楽が好きだった
I always loved music.
I got my first guitar
when I was 15,
ギターを弾き始めたのは15歳のときで—
and since then it’s been my way
of expressing myself.
それからは ギターで自分を表現してきた
When they asked,
“デイブ バンドに入らないか？”
って声をかけられたときは—
“Dave, do you want
to join the band?”
迷わずに応じたよ
I didn’t have to think twice.
Making music,
that’s all that really mattered to me.
音楽を作ることが僕のすべてだった
ミュージシャンになれば
きっと幸せになると思っていた
I thought being a musician
would make me happy.
So that is the path
I followed.
そして その道を歩み続けてきたんだ
Only it is not
what I thought it to be.
でも現実は 思っていたのとは違っていた…
I work here
during the day to pay the bills.
生活のために 日中はここで働いている
I thought my life
would turn out better.
自分の人生はもっと良くなる
と思っていたけど—
But something was missing.
何か物足りなかった…
幸福になるどころか 何かを
失っている気がしていたんだ
Instead of being happy,
I just felt lost.
いけない 集中しなきゃ！
Man, I’m distracted!
感じのいい人たちだな
They are friendly
and look happy.
彼がパンフレットを差し出してこう言った
He gave me a tract and said:
多くの人は本当の幸福を探し求めています
あなたもそうではありませんか？
“Many people are searching
for true happiness.
Maybe you
are one of them.”
This could help.
助けが得られそうだ
すぐに住所を書いて 仕事が終わった後に
訪ねてきてくれないか聞いてみた
I quickly wrote down my address
and asked whether they would mind
passing by after I finished my shift.
確かに僕も 探し求めているんだ
I was searching all right.
実際には 答えはいつも僕の
目の前にあったのかもしれない
Actually, the answers
were in front of me all along.
どうして今まで気付かなかったんだろう
How come I only get it now?
You see,
実は…
バプテスマを受けているんだ
I was baptized.
でも 本当の意味で真理を
受け入れてはこなかった
But I never gave
the truth a chance.
Roy did come as promised.
ロイは約束どおり訪ねてきてくれた
それで “自分はバプテスマを受けた
兄弟です”って打ち明けた
I told him,
“I’m a baptized brother.”
ロイは良く話を聞いてくれた
He really listened to me.
そして 詩編 100:3を
開いてくれたんだ
Then he shared Psalm 100:3:
“Know that Jehovah is God.
“He is the one who made us,
and we belong to him.
We are his people
and the sheep of his pasture.”
In the Bible,
Jehovah is likened to a shepherd.
聖書の中で エホバは
羊飼いに例えられている
He knows
every single one of his sheep,
神はすべての羊をご存じで—
一匹でもいなくなれば
すぐに気付かれるんだ
and he knows
when one goes missing.
いなくなっても
見放されているわけじゃない
A lost sheep is not a lost cause;
it still belongs to him.
まだ神に属する羊なんだ
And Jehovah
doesn’t spare any efforts
エホバはそれを見出すために
どんな努力も惜しまれない
in searching for it
until he finds it.
僕も失われた羊のひとりだ
I was like one of those lost sheep.
でも今もエホバに属している
But I still belonged
to Jehovah,
そして 神は僕のことを
忘れたりされなかった
and he has never
forgotten about me.
ロイはまた会おうと言ってくれた
Roy promised
we would keep in touch
そして日曜日の集会に誘ってくれたんだ
and invited me
to the Sunday meeting.
その朝は本当に緊張したよ
Man, I was nervous
that morning.
I wanted to look my best.
見栄えよくしていかないと
Roy and Matthew
were waiting for me,
ロイとマシューが待っていてくれて
温かく歓迎してくれた
giving me a warm welcome
そのことは絶対に忘れないよ
—something I’ll never forget.
懐かしいな
How I missed this!
This is indeed
Jehovah’s congregation.
これこそエホバの会衆だ
僕の居場所はここにあるんだ
This is where I belong.
真理がこれほどはっきり
理解できたことはなかった
The truth has never
been so clear to me.
兄弟姉妹との親しい交わりは本当に楽しい
How I enjoy the close company
of my brothers and sisters!
What I enjoy most
is helping others
何より楽しいのは—
愛ある父エホバを見出すよう
他の人を助けることだ
to find our loving Father,
Jehovah.
エホバに頼り—
With Jehovah’s help,
I will never be lost again.
僕はもう二度と 迷い出たりはしない
2015年11月のブロード
キャスティングでは—
The November 2015 broadcast stressed
that there is no better place to be
than in Jehovah’s protective arms.
エホバの保護の み腕の中に勝る場所は
ほかにないことが強調されました
Those who have drifted away from Jehovah
were then, and are still now,
今もエホバから漂い出た
ままでいるなら—
遅れることなく行動するよう
励ましたいと思います
warmly encouraged
to act without delay.
ドラマで見たように
エホバは羊を世話し—
As we saw depicted,
Jehovah provides shepherds
ご自分の組織に戻るよう 愛ある仕方で
導いてくれる羊飼いを備えておられます
who care for his sheep
and lovingly guide them
back into his organization.
When the preaching work
was getting started
韓国などの国で宣べ伝える業
が始まったとき—
in such countries
as South Korea,
エホバは兄弟たちを強めるために
宣教者たちを用いました
Jehovah often used missionaries
to help strengthen our brothers.
アーカイブにあるインタビューの中で—
In an archived interview,
Brother Chong-il Park
パク ジョンイル兄弟は
それが自分の奉仕に与えた影響と—
describes the effect
this had on his sacred service
試練にどのように備えさせて
くれたかを説明しています
and how it prepared him
for the trials he would face.
From 1939 on,
our brothers
1939年以降 エホバの組織との
連絡が途絶えたため—
didn’t have any contact
with Jehovah’s organization,
兄弟たちは もう組織は存在しない
と考えていました
and they thought
that no organization existed.
Then, in 1948,
ところが1948年に
一人の兄弟が—
a brother
read from a newspaper
ものみの塔協会の活動に関する
新聞記事を見つけました
about the activity
of Watchtower Society.
And it surprised the brothers.
兄弟たちは驚いて 協会に
手紙を書き送りました
So brothers wrote the Society,
and the Society
was so happy
hearing from Korean brothers,
協会は韓国からの知らせに喜び—
and they answered
韓国語の小冊子を送ってくださいました
with many booklets
in Korean.
There were
two different reactions.
反応は二つに分かれました
Some brothers was excited
about preaching work.
宣教を再開することに
興奮を覚える兄弟たちと—
Yet,
another group questioned:
これがエホバの用いる真の組織なのか
と疑う兄弟たちがいたのです
“Is that true organization
of Jehovah?”
First missionary group
—Brother and Sister Steele—
1949年8月9日 宣教者の第一陣として
スティール兄弟姉妹が到着しました
arrived on August 9, 1949.
スティール兄弟は わたしたちの質問
すべてに答えてくれました
All the questions
were answered
by Brother Steele,
and then
それで兄弟たちはすぐに
一致のうちに宣教に携わりました
right away
brothers were preaching
in unity.
I began pioneering
わたしは1950年に開拓奉仕を始めました
in January 1950.
同じ年の3月には ギレアデを卒業した
宣教者がさらに6名到着しました
And then in March 1950,
six more missionaries
arrived from Gilead School.
We had only one congregation
in Seoul.
当時ソウルには会衆が
一つしかありませんでした
And the missionaries
were busy for many Bible studies.
宣教者たちはたくさんの
聖書研究を司会していて—
So many interested persons
coming to the meetings.
関心を示した大勢の人々が
集会に出席するようになりました
The public talk was arranged
そして 初めての試みとして小学校の
講堂で公開講演が開かれました
in school auditorium
—first time.
And there were
伝道者は60名ほどでしたが—
over 360 people attended,
その日の公開講演には360名を
超える人々が出席しました
whereas the publishers was
about 60.
その同じ日 朝鮮戦争が勃発しました
The same day,
Korean War broke out,
and the missionaries
had to leave
宣教者たちは避難しなければならなくなり
6月27日に日本に逃れました
on 27th of June
to Japan.
多くの兄弟たちが
韓国の南部に避難しました
And then our brothers
had to take refuge
to southern part
of Korea.
I was hiding
in the country.
わたしは市内に隠れていましたが
数日後 共産党の秘密警察に見つかりました
Then few days later,
the secret police
from Communist found us.
We explained to him
クリスチャンなので
戦争には参加できないこと—
as a Christian
we cannot participate in the war,
それで隠れていたことを説明しました
so we had
to hide ourselves.
すると警官は “わたしは宗教に
ついてはよく知らないので—”
And then he says: “Well,
I do not know much about religion,
“so I better take
one of my friends
“宗教に詳しい友人を連れて
きたほうがよさそうだ”
“who knows about religion.
“明日もう一度来るので それまで
ここを離れないように”と言いました
“So I will
come back tomorrow.
Don’t leave from here.”
So, then,
we waited until next day,
そして次の日 その警官は別の警官を
連れてやってきました
and he came with another.
それで わたしは聖書から証言し
戦争や世界で生じている様々な問題が—
So I started preaching
from the Bible
about why
this war broke out
マタイ 24章の預言の成就
であることを説明しました
and the many problems
in the world
and so on,
because the fulfillment
すると彼らは“説明してくれてありがとう
それじゃあ”と言って去っていきました
of Jesus’ prophecy
in Matthew 24.
And then they say,
“Well, thank you very much
for your preaching.”
二日後 二人目の警官が別の友人を連れて
きたので また証言することができました
And then say, “Goodbye.”
Then two days later,
the latter one came
with another friend
so that we could preach to them.
彼らがソウルに留まっていた3か月間
わたしたちは事実上彼らに守られました
During three months
they were staying in Seoul,
and, in fact,
they protected us.
I was picked
by South Korean army
その後 わたしは韓国軍に捕まりました
to serve the back support
そして 前線で戦う兵士をサポートする
仕事を命じられました
of the military
in front line to carry arms
武器を運ぶ仕事です
to the soldiers,
それは受け入れられなかったので—
which I could not accept,
その仕事を拒否しました
so I refused it.
And then
すると ひどく殴られました
I was beaten.
And then one day
ある日のこと その部隊が別の場所に
移動することになりました
this company has to move
to another place.
I hide myself
わたしは天井裏に身を隠しました
in behind the ceiling
so that they don’t notice
皆が移動する際に気付かれない
ようにするためです
when they leave the place.
And the next morning
when I came down,
次の朝 下に降りてみると
部隊は移動した後でした
there was nothing left.
I walked on one street,
toward one direction,
それから通りに出て
ある方向に進んでいくと—
and then I found a sign
「国際聖書研究者協会」と
書かれた看板が見えました
that said
“International Bible Students Association.”
わたしはそこで 兄弟たちと
共に6か月間過ごしました
So I stayed with the brothers
for six months.
Brother Steele
came back from Japan
後にスティール兄弟は
仲間の兄弟たちを世話するため—
by himself to take care
of the brothers.
独りで日本から戻って来られました
In 1952, Brother Steele
recommended me
1952年 兄弟はわたしを
ギレアデ学校に推薦してくださり—
to Gilead School.
So that I was invited
in 22nd class.
第22期のクラスに招待されました
So I took the steps
ところが パスポートを取りに行くと—
政府はわたしが徴兵を終えて
いないことに気付きました
to get the passport.
And then the government find out
that I didn’t serve in military.
わたしは政府から パスポートの代わりに
徴兵の通告書を受け取りました
They gave me draft notice
instead of passport.
So I had to stand
for the neutrality
そして 中立の問題に直面することになり
ギレアデ学校に行くかわりに—
instead of going to Gilead School,
which made me to be confined
軍の刑務所で2年間服役
することになりました
in military prison
for two years.
Then 1958, I was enrolled
1958年 ギレアデ第32期
のクラスに入校しました
in Gilead School in 32nd class.
I really appreciate
学校での素晴らしい訓練に
本当に感謝しています
that great Gilead School training.
Since my job in the branch,
especially in translation work
支部では翻訳の仕事をしていますが
翻訳作業には深い知識が不可欠です
—and translation work
involves much deep knowledge—
ギレアデでの訓練は その面でも
大きな助けになっています
the Gilead training
has certainly helped
in translation work.
The real appreciation
真理と組織に対する感謝や
兄弟たちが示してくださる—
about the truth
and the organization,
謙遜さや温和さなどの特質に対する
感謝や認識を培うことは—
the brothers’ qualities,
the humbleness and meekness,
その手本に倣って全時間奉仕に
打ち込む点で助けとなってきました
certainly it helped me
to follow the examples
to apply
in the full-time service.
Did you note what Brother Park
said he appreciated most
迫害と投獄と耐え忍んだ後—
パク兄弟は何に一番感謝
していたでしょうか？
even after enduring persecution
and prison for his faith?
兄弟たちが示したキリストのような人格と
エホバの組織から受けた訓練です
It was the Christlike qualities
of his brothers
and the training he received
from Jehovah’s organization
これは 共に集まることがもたらす
益のもう一つの例です
—another example of the benefits
that result from our meeting together.
パク兄弟の信仰に倣うための方法に
ついてさらに知りたいなら—
If you’d like to find more ways
to imitate Brother Park’s faith,
2008年12月号の「目ざめよ！」誌
12ページから始まる—
you can read his life story
beginning on page 12
of the December 2008 issue
of Awake!
ライフ・ストーリーをご覧ください
Like many older ones
before them,
年長の人たちのように
若い兄弟姉妹たちは—
younger brothers and sisters
are taking on challenging assignments
霊的にやりがいのある
割り当てに取り組んでいます
that bring them
rich spiritual rewards.
次はインドに行って フランシス・
ロドリゲス兄弟から話を聞きましょう
We go next to India to hear
from Brother Francis Rodrigues.
兄弟は 王国福音宣明者のための
学校の訓練を活用して—
He’s using his training
from the School for Kingdom Evangelizers
インド手話の区域で人々を教えています
to teach people
in the Indian Sign Language field.
若いころ 近くの会衆に
二人の特別開拓者がいて—
エホバにお仕えする
幸福な姿を見ていました
海外で仕事をするという
選択肢もありましたが—
エホバに全時間お仕えすることにしました
特別全時間奉仕をしていると
エホバが必要を顧みてくださいます
神のみ手にある有用な道具として
どこでも用いて頂きたいと願っています
一年前から インド手話の
畑で奉仕しています
奉仕されていない
20ほどの区域を訪問しました
朝7時から ろう者を探す業を始めます
村人の大半は農業をしていて
休憩のために帰ってきます
夜の9時か9時半頃まで奉仕します
それから夜のうちに次の村に移動し—
朝7時には聖書研究を始めます
これを週に4回行ないます
記念式の招待活動を行なっていた
区域に ろう学校がありました
何人かの生徒が走り寄ってきて
“エホバ 愛”と言いました
わたしは どうしてわたしたちを
知っているの？と尋ました
すると 一度だけ集会に来たことのある
少年がいることに気付きました
彼が学校の友達に話したんです
子どもたちは
“一度ここにきて—”
“エホバについてもっと
教えてください”と言いました
学校に一度も通ったことのない
ろう者ともお会いします
そういう場合 両親にも
一緒に座ってもらって—
互いにコミュニケーション
を図る様子を観察し—
彼らの手話に合わせる
ようにしています
10時間ほど離れたある区域で—
最初に関心を示したのは
2,3人のろう者だけでした
しかし 徐々に増え始めました
朝7時から聖書研究を始めましたが
代わる代わる人が来て—
10人から12人のグループで
研究を行なうこともありました
夜の8時半には研究を
終えなければなりません
帰宅するために列車で
10時間かかるからです
支部事務所を訪問する
計画を立てました
見学が終わると二人のろう者の
少女が泣き始め—
“ここにいる兄弟たちから愛を示されて—”
“エホバだけが真の神だ
とわかった”と言いました
それから二人の生活に
変化が生じ始め—
一人はバプテスマを受けていない
伝道者になりました
ろう者が自分たちの生活を
変化させ 幸せになり—
エホバとの良い関係を築いている
様子を見ると 幸福になります
この割り当てには
困難も伴います
村を訪問するために 10時間もかけて
移動すると疲れを感じます
列車が満員のこともあります
帰りの列車が3時間も遅れる
ことだってありますし—
列車が来ないこともあります
困難は生じますが
やがて過ぎ去ります
それに気を取られない
ようにしています
わたしは 困難を取り除くことではなく
それを克服する力を祈り求めます
どんな困難も 経験できる益に
比べれば取るに足りません
それに焦点を合わせれば
自分の割り当てを楽しめます
Brother Rodrigues searches for those
rightly disposed for everlasting life
ロドリゲス兄弟は困難があっても
できるときにはいつも—
永遠の命のために正しく整えられた
人々を見出そうとしています
wherever he can find them
despite the obstacles.
And you may have noted
that his joy comes from directing people
兄弟の喜びは真の霊的
兄弟関係に入るよう—
to the congregation to be part
of our true spiritual brotherhood.
人々を会衆に導き入れる
ことから来ています
That example is repeated millions
of times over through the diligent efforts
世界中の伝道者や開拓者が勤勉な努力を
払って同様に人々を導いています
of publishers and pioneers
around the world.
さらに多くの人々がエホバとの
良い関係を築くよう助けるために—
Why not examine your ministry
to find ways to help
yet more people to build
a good relationship with Jehovah?
自分の宣教を吟味してみるのは
いかがでしょうか？
As we’ve seen
just in this program,
今このプログラムで見たように—
信仰の模範は様々な形で
示されることが分かります
examples of faith
come in a variety of forms.
2016年4月のプログラムで—
In the April 2016 program,
we saw the first two installments
「生命の起源に対する見方」という
シリーズの最初の二つの連載を見ました
in the series
“Viewpoints on the Origin of Life.”
ここで 科学を研究した
ことのある人々が—
We’ll now enjoy two more examples of those
whose backgrounds in scientific study
創造者に対する強い信仰を培った 二つの
実例をさらに見ることにしましょう
enabled them to cultivate
strong faith in the Creator.
わたしはロシーオ・ピカド・ヘレロです
My name
is Rocío Picado Herrero.
スペインのサラマンカ大学で
化学を学びました
I studied chemistry
at the University of Salamanca, in Spain.
有機化学を専攻しました
I specialize in organic chemistry.
This field focuses
on the study of the carbon atom
炭素原子を中心に それに由来する
あらゆる化合物を研究します
and all the compounds
that are derived from this atom.
わたしは生命は進化によって
生じたと信じていました
I believed that life
came about through evolution.
I remember seeing a picture
in a natural science book
異なる脊椎動物の胎芽を描いた
自然科学の本の写真を見て—
that depicted the embryos
of different vertebrates,
成長の初期段階で際立った類似性が
あったのを覚えています
and in the early stages of development,
the similarities were outstanding.
But when I started studying
at the university,
大学で研究を始めてから 進化理論の
過程を詳細に学び始めましたが—
I began studying
in detail the process
on which
the evolution theory is based.
驚いたことに これらの過程は
証明された事実ではありませんでした
To my surprise,
I discovered that these processes
わたしは化学者として 分子内における
原子の分布に非常に関心がありました
were not proven facts.
As a chemist, I’m fascinated
by the distribution
of atoms within a molecule.
In living creatures,
the 20 amino acids
生物には 生命の合成のために必要な
20のアミノ酸があります
that are vital
for the synthesis of life,
それらは生命に必要な
基本タンパク質ですが—
the basic proteins
required for life,
interestingly,
are all levorotatory or left-handed.
興味深いことに そのすべては左旋回
つまり左利きなのです
So when a ray
of polarized light arrives,
それで偏光の光線が当たると
それらのアミノ酸は光を左側にそらせます
these amino acids
divert the light toward the left.
もしこれが成り行きで
生じるのであれば—
There is no explanation for this
because the logical thing would be
半分は右利きで あとの半分は左利きになる
というのが理論的な考え方で—
that if this were a random process,
half would be right-handed
どうしても説明がつきません
and the other half
would be left-handed.
こう自問しました
I asked myself, ‘How could evolution
produce compounds that are levorotatory
進化によって どのように生命に必要な
左旋回の物質が合成できるのだろうか？
and precisely the ones
essential for life?’
ついにわたしは 力ある方
設計者 生命の創造者—
In the end, I had to conclude
that there must be a force,
また命に必要な物質やアミノ酸を作られた方が
おられるに違いないと結論しました
a Designer, a Creator of life
and of the elements
and the amino acids
required for life.
宗教的な環境で育ったものの—
Even though
I had a religious upbringing,
神とは誰かに関してははっきりとした
考えを持っていませんでした
my ideas were not clear
as to who God was.
I merely viewed him
as a Supreme Being
言い開きをしなければならない
至高者としか見ていませんでした
before whom
we would be held accountable.
聖書は科学の教科書ではありません
The Bible
is not a science textbook.
それはこの宇宙や宇宙を制御している法則を
説明するための本ではありません
Its purpose is not to describe
the universe we live in
or the laws
that regulate our universe.
But when it does mention science,
でも科学や科学的なことを
述べる点で 非常に正確です
and when it discusses scientific matters,
it does so with great accuracy.
そして 間違いなく最大の益は—
And undoubtedly the greatest benefit
is that it allows me to enjoy
聖書が 科学的な見地からして
わたしを魅了してやまない宇宙の—
a personal relationship
with the Creator of the universe
創造者との個人的な関係を
楽しめるようにしてくれることです
—a universe that fascinates me
from a scientific perspective.
My name is Davey Loos.
わたしはデイビー・ルースです
I studied biochemistry
at the University of Leuven in Belgium,
ベルギーのルーヴェン大学で生化学を
学び 博士号も取得しました
and after that time
I did a PhD in the same area.
When I was a young child,
I believed in the Bible.
子どものころは聖書を
信じていましたが—
But growing up,
I kind of lost my interest in it.
成長するにつれて関心は
薄らいでいきました
When you go to university
and you study life sciences
大学で生命科学や生化学を
学び始めると—
or biochemistry, for example,
すぐに生命の起源や進化論に
ついて教えられます
you get introduced into the idea
of the origin of life very quickly
and also into the principle
of evolution.
The professors
who taught these courses,
教えている教授たちは 長年の経験と
地位のある科学者たちばかりで—
they were really scientists
with long careers,
人々から尊敬されてもいます
and they were well-established scientists,
and we had a lot of respect for them.
それで 進化論について疑問を差し挟むこと
など考えられませんでした
So there was just no way to really question
the principle of evolution.
1999年 コソボ紛争がおきました
In 1999, there was a war
in Europe—in Kosovo—
わたしは 子どもの頃に
読んだ聖書の中に—
and I remember reading
in the Bible as a child
将来起きる出来事が予告されて
いたことを思い出しました
about the future events
that would take place,
コソボでの紛争もその中の一つ
なのではないかと思うようになり—
and I started wondering whether the war
in Kosovo was one of those events.
再び聖書を手に取りました
So that lead me
to pick up the Bible again.
そして 生命の起源や進化論に関しても
自分の信条を再吟味すべきだと感じました
At the time, I felt that I had to reexamine
my beliefs about the origin of life
and also about the principle
of evolution.
Based on the theory of evolution,
we would expect to see
進化論が正しいとすれば—
化石の記録の中には進化の課程にあるものを
たくさん見出せるはずです
an abundance of transitional forms
to be present in the fossil record.
しかし 化石の証拠を調べてみても
それは見出せませんでした
But when we do look at the fossil evidence,
we just don’t see that.
We see that the major species
主だった種は ある特定の時に
存在するようになり—
come into existence
at specific times,
and their form and structure
is still exactly the same
その形や構造は今日に至るまで
変わっていません
as their form
and structure today.
It was actually Darwin himself
who wrote in his book
実際 ダーウィン自身も
自らの本の中で—
that the biggest objection
that could be brought against this theory
進化論に対して最も大きな
異論を唱えるのは—
would be the fact
that the fossil record
化石の記録に進化の途上にあるものを
見出せないという事実だろうと書いています
does not show an abundance
of transitional forms.
And that’s what really happens
if you look at the set of data
実際に記録をたどっていけば—
化石の記録は進化論とは反対のことを
示していることがわかります
—the fossil record seems to prove
the opposite of evolution.
As a biochemist,
I had the opportunity to learn about
生化学者として 数多くの異なる生体分子を
調べ 研究してきました
and study
many different biomolecules.
And I observed
that pretty much every biomolecule
そして それらの生体分子が本当に
複雑な分子であることがわかりました
is really a complex molecule.
We can look at them
as nanoscale molecular motors
極めて複雑な動きをする—
ナノスケールの分子モーターを
観察すればそのことは明らかです
or machines that are performing
very complex and specific tasks.
自然界や分子の中に見られる
精緻な造りは—
For me, the complexity that we see in nature
and the complexity in those molecules
創造者が確かにおられる
ことを証ししています
points to the fact
that there really is a Creator.
Did you see common ground
that could help you
進化を信じている人との話し合いに
役立つ土台を見出せましたか？
in your next discussion
with someone who believes in evolution?
ピカド・ヘレロ姉妹が化学を探求して
設計者がいる証拠を見つけたとき—
When Sister Picado Herrero’s
chemistry research
showed evidence of design,
子どもの時に神について考えていた
事柄を思い出しました
she called to mind her view of God
from her religious upbringing.
進化を信じている人も
幼い時から持っていた—
The person you meet
who believes in evolution
神に関する答えの出ていない
疑問を持っているかもしれず—
might also have unanswered questions
about God from their upbringing,
あなたが創造者に関する
分かりやすい証拠を示すなら—
and they may respond
to the simple evidences
of a Creator
that you present.
答え応じるかもしれません
ルース兄弟は 世界の出来事を見て
自分の信仰を再吟味しました
Brother Loos
was moved by world events
to pick up the Bible
and reexamine his beliefs.
強固な進化論者を含めて—
Everyone we meet,
even firm believers in evolution,
すべての人は世界の状況の
影響を受けているので—
are affected by world conditions
and may listen to our message of hope.
希望の音信に耳を傾けるかもしれません
それで 進化を信じている人でも—
So when someone says
that he believes in evolution,
良いたよりを聞かないと
早急に結論しないでください
don’t be quick to assume
that he’ll reject the good news.
実際 ペースを緩めたり
時間をとったりするなら—
Really, our ministry
and other aspects of life often improve
物事は改善することは
少なくありません
when we slow down,
take our time,
今月のミュージックビデオは
次のように勧めています
and as our music video admonishes:
“Don’t Run Fast.”
“走らないで”
You can walk, but please don’t run.
It’s hard to do when you’re having fun.
あるこう はしらずに
おもいきり はしゃぎたいよね
だけど かんがえよう
But there’s a reason we don’t race;
When you’re with the friends,
みんなのこと たいせつに
It’s not the time or place.
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
はしらないで
あいを まなぼう
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
きっと できるよ
はしらないで
You’ve got things you have to do,
People to serve, who depend on you.
役に立ちたくて
目もくれず 前に向かう
But don’t forget why you’re here;
Learn to love the friends;
だけど 思い出そう
君がいるのは 友のため
Let them know you care.
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
あせらないで
愛を つなごう
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
きっと 変わるよ
あせらないで
You can run to someone’s door.
Is there someone home?
家から家に
いそぐけど 返事はない
Well, you’re not real sure.
But look around and see everyone,
だけど 立ち止まろう
人はいるよ すぐそこに
People walking by. Can you talk to one?
いそがないで
Don’t run so fast.
Take your time and make things last.
愛を 広げよう
Learn to love the things you do.
Just don’t run fast.
きっと 届くよ
いそがないで
Oh. Just don’t run fast!
Oh
いそがないで
Of course, we shouldn’t run
at all in the Kingdom Hall.
王国会館の中では
走ってはなりません
しかし 比ゆ的な意味で
早く走らないようにとのこの助言は—
But in a figurative sense,
this counsel, not to run fast,
applies to more
than just our young ones.
若者だけに当てはまる
ものではありません
As we saw, even when we’re busy
with important theocratic work,
重要な神権的な業に忙しい時でも—
考え 鼓舞し 兄弟たちを励ますためにも
時間を取ることができます
we can still take the time
to consider, incite,
and encourage our brothers.
野外奉仕において急いで
区域を回るよりも—
And rather than rushing
through our field service,
人々を探して心に達することに努めた
イエスに見倣いましょう
we want to imitate
Jesus’ focus on finding people
and reaching hearts.
エホバは 多くの方法でわたしたちの
心を動かしてくださいます
Jehovah reaches our hearts
in ever so many ways,
すでに2016年「エホバに
忠節を保ちましょう！」地区大会に—
such as when we attend
our spiritual gatherings.
By now, some of you
have already attended
出席した人もおられるでしょう
the 2016 “Remain Loyal to Jehovah!”
regional convention.
でも わたしたちの多くは—
興奮を誘う三日間を これから
楽しむことになっています
But millions of us still have
an exciting three days ahead
47の良く準備された話—
with 47 well-prepared talks,
エホバに歌うための18曲の歌—
18 songs that we’ll
sing to Jehovah,
50以上のオーディオと
ビデオのプログラムー
and more than 50 audio
and video presentations,
そして2つの長編ドラマが提供されます
including 2 feature-length dramas.
これらのプログラムすべては—
All of these program parts
have been prepared to help us
難しい問題があっても神に忠節を保つのを
助けるために準備されました
remain loyal to God
despite serious challenges.
例えば ストレスや誘惑にあったとき
どのように忠節を保てるでしょうか？
For instance,
how can we maintain our loyalty
when under stress or temptation?
エホバはわたしたちの忠節を強める—
What did Jehovah
personally teach Job
どんなことをヨブに個人的に
教えられたでしょうか？
that can strengthen
our loyalty?
And why does the Bible say
that Jehovah’s loyal love
なぜ聖書は
エホバの忠節な愛は—
命そのものよりも尊い
と述べているのでしょうか？
is more precious than life itself?
To find out more
of what you can expect,
さらに多くの益を得るために
大会のプログラム全体を概観してください
review the full convention program,
which can be downloaded
from jw.org.
それはjw.org から
ダウンロードできます
You won’t want to miss any part
「 エホバに忠節を保ちましょう！」
大会のどの部分も逃したくはないでしょう
of the “Remain Loyal to Jehovah!”
convention program!
As we close,
we bring you greetings
最後に パナマのラス・ペルラス・ヌベレ
会衆からのあいさつをお送りします
from the Las Perlas-Ngäbere
congregation in Panama.
ボルカン地区は
国で最も高地にあり—
The Volcán region
is the highest point in the country,
涼しい気候のため
コーヒーや様々な野菜が育ちます
enjoying a cool climate
for growing coffee
and a variety of vegetables.
収穫の最盛期である10月から12月には
ヌベレ語を話す大勢の人々がやってきます
The busy harvest work
from October to December
brings large numbers
of Ngäbere-speaking people
to the area.
親切な気質の人々なので—
Their kind nature gives our brothers
excellent opportunities
兄弟たちはこの素晴らしい機会を活用して
神の王国について教えています
to teach them
about God’s Kingdom.
Local brothers and sisters
地元の兄弟姉妹たちは—
provide regular support
to the Ngäbere Remote Translation Office.
ヌベレ語遠隔翻訳事務所を
定期的にサポートしています
And some are making the effort
その言語を学ぶ努力を払い—
to learn the language to assist
in the congregation’s spiritual harvest.
会衆の霊的収穫を援助している
兄弟たちもいます
わたしたちからの温かいクリスチャン愛
とあいさつをお返しし—
We send them
our warm Christian love
and greetings in return and pray for them
to continue in their zealous spirit.
兄弟たちが熱心な霊を保って
励むよう祈りたいと思います
We thank you and hope
you’ve enjoyed our program.
今月のプログラムを
楽しまれたことでしょう
ニューヨーク市 ブルックリンから
JW Broadcastingでした
This is JW Broadcasting
from Brooklyn, New York!